Guide to the Young Democratic Club of Montana records 1936-1939
Montana Historical Society
Young Democratic Club of Montana records
1936-1939
Montana Historical Society Archives
MC 184
Young Democratic Club of Montana
.75 linear feet of shelf space
These records of the Young Democratic Club of Montana consist of the personal working files (1936-1939) of Gail Meagher Brown as secretary, editor, national committee woman, and regional representative. Included are general correspondence, organizational materials, subject files, newsletters, and miscellany.
State officers for the Young Democratic Club of Montana were first elected in 1933. The organization was affiliated with the Young Democratic Clubs of America. The purpose of the organization was to contribute to the growth and influence of the Democratic Party, to develop leadership, and to maintain and promote harmony within the party ranks. The membership was organized in county clubs of Young Democrats chartered by the Executive Committee of the Young Democratic Club of Montana. Officers were elected for one year by a majority vote of delegates to the annual state convention. Elected officers included a president, a vice-president, a secretary, and a treasurer. Members in good standing of any chartered club were eligible to hold state offices provided they were over twenty-one and under thirty-five years of age. The State Executive Committee was composed of two state committeemen and two state committeewomen elected by county clubs from each congressional district, the elected officers of the organization, and the state's representatives ("national committeeman and committeewoman") appointed to attend the annual convention of the Young Democratic Clubs of America. State and national annual conventions were governed by votes of members of chartered clubs. The major activity of the state organization between 1936 and 1938 was to promote memberships in local county chartered clubs. County clubs held meetings and sponsored social events to raise funds to defray the cost of charter membership to the Young Democratic Club of Montana. In 1936 Gail Meagher Brown of Helena became secretary of the Young Democratic Club of Montana. In 1937 she was appointed committeewoman to the national organization, as Montana's representative. In 1938 Gail Brown also served as director of the Young Democratic Clubs of America's Region Ten, which included Montana, North Dakota, and South Dakota. In addition, she produced and edited the state club's newsletter, Montana Young Democrat.
Content Description:
Records. 1936-1939. .75 linear foot. This collection consists of the personal working files of Gail Meagher Brown, accumulated during her tenure as secretary of the Young Democratic Club of Montana, editor of the Montana Young Democrat, and national committeewoman to and regional representative for the Young Democratic Clubs of America. The records include general correspondence (1936-1939) between Gail Brown and other members of the Young Democratic Club of Montana, in particular Elnora Jung of Great Falls, assistant secretary and historian, and Plentywood attorney Vernon B. Hoven, president. Also included are organizational materials (undated); subject files (1937-1938), consisting of the state organization's newsletters and related materials from local chapters concerning county news and activities; and miscellany.
Arranged by series
Acquisition information available upon request
Artifacts separated to Museum. See inventory below for more information.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Young Democratic Club of Montana
Political Parties; Women in Politics
Montana; Government and Politics; Women
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Subject Files
  - "Convention" (re state convention; includes related materials including list of delegates, minutes, summary of speech by Burton K. Wheeler, and program), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - "Convention Book" (re publication of national convention program book as fundraiser), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Lewis and Clark County (includes president's report), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Montana Young Democrat (includes newsletters), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Montana Young Democrat (includes newsletters, and biography of President Vernon Hoven), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Montana Young Democrat (includes newsletters), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Montana Young Democrat (includes newsletters), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Montana Young Democrat (includes newsletters, mailing lists, and copy of minutes of the executive board meeting in Lewistown), 1936-1938 undated (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - "National" (includes reports of meetings within region by Gail M. Brown, brochure re history of Young Democrats, and constitution of Young Democratic Clubs of America), 1936-1937 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - "National Meeting" (includes minutes of National Committee in St. Louis, and list of Club's officers 1937), 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - "National" (includes list of dues paid by state, rules and regulations concerning charters, minutes of National Committee, and president's report), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - National Young Democrats (includes news clippings on club events, and lists of Montana subscribers), 1937 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - "Regional", 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - "Regional Director" (includes lists of directors of all national regions and of state and county officers in region), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - "Seattle Rally" (includes four editions of Rally News), 1938 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - "State" (includes reports re conventions in Billings, Polson, and Havre; copy of constitution of the Young Democratic Club of Montana; and report of executive committee, 1936), 1936-1937 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - "State" (includes lists of delegates to annual convention, Lewis and Clark county officers, and state officers; copy of standard constitution for counties; and correspondence re history of Democrats in Judith Basin County), 1937-1938 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
  - "State" (includes report re convention in Roundup), 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
  - "State" (includes report of state officers for 1939), 1938-1939 (Box-folder 2 / 4)
- Organizational Records
  - Drafts of constitutions, undated (Box-folder 2 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - Democratic Digest (includes subscription forms and lists of subscriptions taken over from "National Young Democrats"), 1938 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Donkey Stuff (includes newsletter of Cascade County Young Democrats), 1937 (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - List of materials transferred to the Museum (Box-folder 2 / 8)
  - Miscellaneous (includes history of Young Democratic Club of Montana, and lists of officers), 1933-1935 (Box-folder 2 / 9)